Hi, it's repair time. This one's from
home. It's my old Goal Zero Yeti 400. As
the name suggests, 400 watt hour
battery. It's one of these, you know,
little portable things. We use it to
take camping. We just used it like 6
months ago for camping. It's been
working great for years. You might have
seen this in one of my second channel
videos. This one actually powers my
solar assistant Raspberry Pi from the
USB output here. And that does all my
solar monitoring from the DI inverter.
And well, I've got to admit, it looks
like I've goofed it because this thing
ordinarily powers that Raspberry Pi, but
I was mucking around with my solar setup
at home and I actually like normally
it's powered from this external plug
pack here which can power from like, you
know, external solar panel up to
never exceed 22 volts input here. This
is like a 16 volt plug pack. And it's
normally just floats at 100% there and
unless actually take it somewhere and
use it. And it powers that Raspberry Pi,
but unfortunately, I was mucking around
with it and I accidentally disconnected
the mains to it. So my Raspberry Pi
solar assistant worked for like a week
or something until it suddenly stopped
working. And I, you know, was checking
my solar thing on my shoe phone and it's
like, it's not talking. Oh, it might
need to reboot it or something. And I
went back out and went out there to
investigate and sure enough, this
battery was completely flat. Womp womp
womp womp. And this is what happens when
I plug it in. Watch this. Hopefully,
you'll see there's an input lead here
and you might see this screen actually
light up
briefly and this lead comes up. It It
just Yeah, it flashes off and it looks
like it doesn't charge at all. So it
looks like it's drained to a point where
it can't charge anymore, which is a
design oversight of this Goal Zero Yeah,
yeah, you saw it actually flash again.
It sort of periodically does that, but
I've actually left it on there for many
days, actually, you know, hoping that
it'll just eventually recover or
whatever.
Um and it doesn't. So, yeah, um that's a
bad design. Yep, yep, there we go. It
just It just hiccuped again and tried to
start, but as I said, left it there for
days and it doesn't seem to overcome
this. So, it looks like the internal
batteries have drained to a point where
it just can't start up at the charging
system or whatever, and it just doesn't
recover. So, it basically killed itself
by letting itself run flat, which is,
yeah, dumb. This is like a really old
model. I don't have done it, you know,
it's not current. They've got, you know,
several generations um
beyond this one now, but um yeah, it's
always been a good little unit. So,
that's But, I've never actually let it
drain down to absolute zero before. So,
if it's some other fault, it's a
genuinely huge coincidence. But, no, I
think I did it by just draining this
thing, sucking, you know, a couple of
watts out of here to drive a Raspberry
Pi, leave it running for a week, and
eventually wah wah wah wah. Anyway,
let's see if we can open this thing. So,
I am actually down here in the dungeon
cuz I don't want to work on like
relatively high-capacity lithium-ion
batteries up in the lab, you know, if a
fire happens, I do have my fire
extinguisher down here, and there's no
fire sensor down in here. So, I'm not
going to get an $1,800 bill. Um I am
using my Swiss tools set. Somebody
personalized this for me and sent it in
through the mailbag like a donkey's
years ago. Let's crack into this thing.
I don't think I've ever done a teardown
of this Oh.
Oh. That's just Oh, that's that's
plastic.
TURN IT OH, AFTER
THAT'S THE HANDLE. OH GOD, I WAS FOOLED.
THERE YOU GO, LIFT that up. Oh, that
didn't make sense. So, yeah, they molded
it that in there just to confuse me.
So, yeah, I might have uh just opened
this up. Oh, wait. Yes, I might have
opened this up myself once, but uh
I've never Oh, that's That's nice. That
just comes off. There's nothing
nothing in there at all. So,
yeah, I don't think I've ever done a
teardown
video of this. Let's have a squeeze. Oh,
that looks pretty neat, does it not? Uh
I don't have my regular poker here. It's
gone missing, but uh yeah, we've got our
big heat sink along there. We've got uh
seal pads there for our drivers, and
there's another couple of devices down
there with some seal pads.
Um
anyway,
this looks pretty neat. Uh that's
interesting. Um input blade fuses there.
Um didn't expect to see
those, but I guess that makes sense.
Anyway, um that's obviously coming from
uh the battery. Look at that, big and
beefy. First thing I can do is actually
uh measure that pack and see what it is
because um probably the easiest way to
fix this would be to use an external,
you know, disconnect um all of this from
the battery, and then uh sort of like
slowly trickle charge the battery from
an external supply, and get it back in
business cuz I suspect that's what's
happening here is that it's just drained
to a point where it doesn't have enough
voltage startup voltage um to start up,
and some protective thing is kicking in,
and it's just
badly designed in the sense that it
would allowed itself to actually drain
uh below a point where it would actually
um
start back up. Got a fan on either side
here, which is pretty decently uh
designed. So, you know, it obviously
sucks in one side and it blows out the
other. That's what she said. Those caps
don't look special at all. Sorry, this
is not my best camera. This is not my
best uh light down here. So, this board
looks like just the uh 240-V mains
inverter for it. So, we've got the
battery coming in here, and the output,
the uh 240-V output uh goes over here to
the uh main socket on the front down
there. It's only got like It's not It's
not huge power. What is it uh 300 W, you
know, 1,200 V um surge. You know, it's
good for like little uh fridges and
stuff when we're out uh camping and
lights and other um sorts of things like
that, but you know, nothing serious. Um
you know, you're not going to go out
there and use your power drill with it.
And we've got another set of beefy red
and black wires coming from the battery
pack down there up to this main
controller board up here. So, it it
looks like two different heavy-duty
wires coming from the battery pack down
there. I was hoping not to have to take
this completely apart cuz the battery
pack's like down in here. It's I'm sure
it's all messy to kind of like Although,
it looks like Yeah, I I can get the I
can There you go. I can just lift out
the front panel there. That's pretty
good. Oh, there you go. Look at that.
Oh.
Are they in-line Are they in-line
connectors? We've got our
rechargeable lithium-ion battery. There
it is. Aha, found my uh yellow poker. I
knew it was down here somewhere. So,
those two big-ass battery wires, they're
just soldered directly down in the PCB
there. They're thick as. Got some
switching transistors there.
Uh and well, there's not much else
doing.
There's a processor on there, as you'd
expect. That's driving all the front
panel LCD. And it looks like it's just,
you know, powering like the USB um
outputs and stuff like that. We've got a
cigarette lighter input here for those
who remember the cigarette lighter in
cars. Does anyone actually still use
one? Uh there we go. Yep. Out of here as
well. They're also going up to the main
uh inverter uh board up there. So, there
you go. That is a big-ass connector
right there. I
presume that they're just paralleled
in there without taking all that out. I
mean, it's not like they would you know
split the battery or anything like that
at all. Just be the one big series
parallel banking there and they're just
running separate wires out just from a
you know a power distribution
point of you know wiring distribution
point of view. And one goes out to the
AC inverter board on top and the other
one just goes over to our main board
here. So, well, I can actually measure
that. Can measure the ohms key between
two those two and it should be
nothing. So, let's just do that. But
yes, there you go. Yeah, they're just
you know there might be some extra
protection on the board up there. It's
probably got some extra protection as I
said there's some extra fusing up the
top here on the mains input. Although
this one down here,
yeah, yep, yep, I see a oh yeah, it
looks like they just have some SMD
fusing there as well. But not as serious
as the main side. And it looks like our
BMS wiring. Although it could it could
actually be on the main board and they
might just be tapping these off. This
actually just joins into It's
interesting. It goes from this wiring
harness into this ribbon cable here via
this inline connector here. So, that's
rather unusual. There you go. It's 10.8
V pack. That's lower than I thought.
40 amp hours there. 427
watt hours nominal capacity. Not sure
what it have these days. It's
not sure how long I've had this.
Probably Oh jeez, it could be 10 years
old. Not sure actually. There you go.
We've got three extra pairs of switching
transistors on the back of that heat
sink as well we couldn't see before.
Okay, let's see what voltage this thing
is at. I'm going to be very disappointed
if it's let itself drain down to
something drastically small.
Zero. Zero. Hello. DC volts. Yeah.
You'll uh
Beuller? Beuller? Well, what's obviously
going on here is that some sort of a
protection board on here which will have
over voltage protection, it'll have
under voltage protection and under
voltage lockout, which is what it's
probably doing here. I mean, there's no
electrochemistry reason why this battery
is at absolute zero
just from, you know, doing this. So,
obviously, it's gotten below a threshold
on the battery protection on there where
it's literally disconnected the battery
to actually protect itself. So, at least
they did something right cuz otherwise
there's no way we're going to be reading
zero on there. So, I think I suspect I'm
pretty reasonably confident that once we
connect an external supply to this
thing, that will then overcome that and
it'll charge up. But why it's like sort
of like doing that hiccup in,
yeah, I'm not 100% sure yet. But anyway,
I'm pretty confident that that battery
hasn't like completely come and got sir.
I think it's actually protected itself
with under voltage lockout. And yeah, we
can just should be able to get that
started again. But why it can't do it on
its own off its own bat,
I don't know. That sucks. All right,
everything's disconnected. So, let's
just plug this in and see if it
Yes, it comes on, stays on, and I'm not
sure if you're seeing that with the
light. It's flishy flashing at 20%
there. Like it's doing something, but
there's obviously they didn't design in
an error indicator on this LCD cuz this
is not a this is a like a segmented LCD,
it's not a graphic LCD. All I had was a
Raspberry Pi hooked up to the USB here.
It should have intelligently, once the
battery was low, it should have disabled
the output here.
Like what the heck crap design is this?
Like Goal Zero is a pretty big brand.
They're one of the like the leaders out
there. Um granted, this is like a really
old model, but damn, very disappointed.
Next thing I want to try here is to hook
the battery back up, but I'll leave the
uh inverter up the top, that inverter
board, I'll leave that flapping around
in the breeze, and let's see if it it
what it does now.
Here we go.
Yeah, whoa, whoa. Oh, oh, it's doing
better. It's doing better. It's flashing
better.
Are you seeing that? Yeah, so it's
flashing differently. It's like
hiccuping very differently, almost
consistently than what it does before
when it had, I guess, the extra load of
that inverter board on the top there.
Look at it.
That's one sick puppy. Oh, I can get in
there and measure the voltage actually
at the same time. I can disconnect the
negative here to see if it's actually
attempting to do
something. There you go. It's attempting
to do something. There you go, 9.3 V.
So, it's attempting to 9.34.
9.35. OH, 9.36.
This is not drifting. This is like
actually it looks like the battery is
perhaps Oh, sorry. Are you seeing that?
It is now. Yeah, 9.42. If I leave it
9.43. Come on, you can do it. Yes. 9.44.
Come on.
You can do it. It looks like it's slowly
accepting a charge now.
So, that is good. You know, I can hook
on an external lab supply and try and
slowly charge it and stuff, but oh, the
little
ring's come off. Um but, it looks like I
don't have to. My Band-Aid's falling
off.
There we go. I'll take that off. Ah, put
a new one on before I get to the gym
tonight. So, I'm going to actually leave
that cuz I'm just Oh, oh, look. LOOK.
IT'S OH, IT'S PERMANENTLY ON NOW. YEP.
YEP, it's permanently on. It is
charging. Input 53 watts, 50 watts.
There you go. So, it's char it's
charging the battery. All I had to do
was disconnect
the inverter up here. It was drawing too
much like peak load when it was coming
on when the battery was flat, I guess so
to speak. But, I'm pretty confident that
well that that 50 watts has to be going
somewhere and it's actually measuring
that using a current shunt on the board
somewhere. It's actually measuring uh
the input power going to the battery.
So, it looks like it's accepted a
charge. Just the mere threat the mere
threat of me um getting out the big
guns, getting out the benchtop power
supply and threatening uh it with a good
time, that it's said, "Okay, I will
cooperate and I will start charging."
But, yeah, that's interesting. So, now I
expect there to be nothing wrong with
this thing. Yeah, it's definitely now
accepting a charge. So, that 50 watts is
going into the battery. No worries
whatsoever. So, I'll come back in an
hour or two and I suspect what's going
to happen is once that battery is uh got
sufficient charge to now boot this thing
um on like normal, then we can hook up
uh rehook up the uh 240 volt uh mains
inverter in there and then that's
obviously taking some surge current in
there that the processor or something
didn't like and then it was hiccuping
the actual processor was hiccuping.
That's uh called that flashing that we
uh saw before. It was trying to start
up, but that inverter up there had too
big a input capacitance on it and it
just didn't like it and it was like,
"Nah,
nah, I'm going to shut back down." And
then it tries to start up again period
and then it
not shuts down again. But, because
there's very little uh like capacitance
in here uh for example, very little uh
surge uh current to charge up when you
initially uh turn it on, it the
processor um in there, the controller
was just happy with that. Now it's
cooperating. So, um yeah, I think once
that's back up in business, I expect to
be able to hook that back up, and Bob's
your uncle, I think that's our repair.
Sorry, another one of my it's
interesting, but I don't think there's
going to be an electronics repair here.
I think it's um didn't even have to get
out lab power supply. Ah, well, I'm
going to call that a win. What are we up
to at the moment?
Oh, yeah, 9.91.
Come on, you can do it. Anyway, I got to
say I do otherwise like uh the
construction of this thing. It's a big
extruded aluminum uh case like this.
It's very nice with just a cutout uh in
the front. So, it's like rugged as, and
these plastic inserts just like slide
into here, so they're not going to come
off unless you absolutely like uh smash
them off or slide them um up. Same thing
with the uh grills. They've got like big
uh deep grooves in there, so they slide
in. So, it's a it's a really nice um
physical design. I I rather like it.
It's just a shame that uh they allowed
the damn thing to like kill itself by
draining itself. Unbelievable Yeah, you
had one job. Just turn off once the
battery reaches low.
Ah, it's not rocket science. Actually,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
disconnect that. Oh, that's right, I
can't actually switch this off. Um it's
like it's it's got a light button, but
it basically stays on like all the time.
See if it's held that. Yes, 9.91 volts.
Oh, there we go, just dropped to 9.90.
Maybe, but you know, it's it's barely
even got any charge in it at the moment.
So, All right, I'm back from the gym. I
got new Band-Aids, and they held. So, we
are at 38%. That's not too shabby. So,
that looks like it's just charging
exactly like it normally would. So, that
should now have plenty of juice in it.
There we go, 11.04 V. No worries. So, I
think I'll hook up the AC inverter back
and I think we'll be right. I'll manage
the cables again
before I put it back together. That is
probably like switching the power
through No, no, that comes straight from
the battery. So, that's going straight
on there and then they'll have the
signal coming from this over here. So,
we're still good. Let's turn the
inverter on.
Oh,
that's all right. I've got the output
disconnected. Output 11 W. Yeah, it
actually draws a substantial amount of
quiescent current just sitting there
switching its little pants off. I've got
it fed up the clacker there. And oh,
yep, there it is. 230
V I've got to set for. No, this is 245 V
I get here in the lab rubbish. So, that
looks like my theory was correct in that
yeah, this thing just went into
undervoltage lockout on the battery
management
or the battery protection in there. It's
not the battery management system. The
management system has to do with like
the charging and the cell balancing and
stuff like that. Still not sure if
that's done under there or
because they got multiple wires coming
out here, it might be done by that PIC
micro in there. But anyway, that's
neither here nor there. So, it could not
get out of that undervoltage lockout and
start recharging itself
while the AC inverter was connected cuz
it had like too much load on it that was
just
preventing the
battery protection in there from coming
back on. Or the exact mechanism we don't
know until unless we've got the
schematic and we did further
investigation. But there you go, that's
an interesting
thing. I don't know like is there I'll
be generous to them and say it could be
the fact that this is quite an old
battery. I haven't cycled it a lot, but
it is actually quite old. So, maybe with
its age, the ESR's increased and that
didn't give it enough juice, but it just
to like start up an inverter like this,
it's not That's not a massive amount of
inrush current or Well, you know,
I don't know. Thoughts in the comments
down below, but jeez, let that be a
lesson to you. When you're designing a
battery like this, make sure you
actually design it to be drained down
and then, like absolutely use the heck
out of it and then like I would use like
really depleted age batteries on the
thing as part of the testing and part of
the design testing for this thing to
make sure that yeah, it can actually
start up and charge again. But, the damn
thing couldn't with that load on there,
but once I removed the AC inverter load,
Bob's your uncle and she was able to
recover. So, maybe they could have had
the undervoltage lockout just set too
low and it just didn't have the juice
available to do it, but I Given that
this thing does not have an actual power
switch, I I kid you not, right? That
else like you can probably see it. That
LCD is still on. So, that micro is still
running. The LCD's still going, but
granted that could take, you know, like
microamps, right? Tens of my microamps
just to keep that small segmented LCD
going, so didn't take a lot, but
ultimately, you know, could eventually
drain down, but great like I was using
the USB-C output on here, but this the
micro here, this PIC micro should have
determined that Oh, okay, battery like,
you know, should get low battery and
then shut off the USB output here, where
I don't think it did. I think it just
kept it on like I wasn't there to watch
it in real time, but I could test that,
but I'm not going to
do it in this video. Um, but yeah, I
assume that it just it just kept pumping
out powering my Raspberry Pi Pi doing
the absolute best it could to power my
load and it didn't shut down and
preserve itself and it completely come a
gutsa couldn't restart. So, yeah, that
is a wah wah wah wah fail in the design
of this thing. So, there you go. That is
not an electronics repair, but that is
interesting nonetheless. So, if you did
find it interesting, give it a big
thumbs up. As always, discuss down below
and over on the EEVblog forum, of
course, the best forum on the interwebs.
And if you want to get my meters, you
can get those on EEVblog.store.
Catch you next time.